[Music]
this program is brought to you by
Stanford University please visit us at
stanford.edu
first of all I want to show you what
difference a sign can make and in
particular the sign that
occurs we've studied an entangled state
of two electrons
we could call it up down and then there
are two possibilities well there's more
than two possibilities but there are two
interesting situations with a plus or
minus in other words you can take your
choice we can study plus and we can
study minus plus minus down up so this
is two
electrons and the state that we're
writing down is a linear superposition
of
States when one electron one is up this
one
two electron one is up electron two is
down so you know what that looks like
looks like
this and then the other component of the
state just flip them
over and uh we can superpose them with a
plus sign or a minus sign
they don't sound so different in either
case there's a good deal of correlation
between the two spins if one of them is
up then the other one is surely down and
if one of them is down the other one is
surely up in both cases the probability
incidentally nothing I'm going to say
right now is going to depend on whether
we we should normalize it correctly in
fact let's put the normalization in
square < TK of
two uh to make the probabilities add up
to
one uh
uh in both
cases the sums well and what was I going
to say in both cases in both cases the
spins are opposite to each
other or the or the three the third
component of spin is opposite to each
other so what is the big difference
between these states and they're quite
different they're quite different and we
want to spend a little bit of time
explaining that uh before I do let me
write a uh a list again a list of the
action of the various Sigma operators
it's the same list that I wrote same
table that I wrote last time first of
all Sigma 1 on up equals down we'll make
reference to this regularly Sigma 1 on
down equals
up Sigma 2 on what is it Sigma 2 on
up uh is I believe I *
down but Sigma 2 on down is is min - I *
up and sigma 3 on up is up and sigma3 on
down is minus
down that's the action of the matrices
Sigma 1 Sigma 2 and sigma 3 on the igen
states of Sigma 3 itself so we'll we'll
make reference to that list as we go
along now in both of these
states the expectation value of any
component of the spin let's say Sigma
we're going to remember now that Sigma
refers to the first electron too which
is an identical family of operators
identical except when it acts it acts on
the Second Spin instead of the first
spin Sigma and too are the two spin
operators this Sigma 1 Sigma 2 and sigma
3 and in either of these states the
expectation value of any component of
Sigma or to is
zero so there is no
direction in which uh either the first
spin or the Second Spin is definitely
polarized there is no
Direction uh that you can pick that you
will know that the spin has to be come
out up in that
direction that is of course different
than any state that you would make for a
single electron and so this is some sort
of entangled state that is not a
simple uh jux position of a spin in a
state times another spin in its own
state they're mixed together in some uh
in some entangled
way okay so first of all every component
in this state of the sigma I are equal
to zero and the to eyes are equal to
zero in this particular State and you
can check that I think we checked it
last time didn't we I think you showed
that for the minus sign is it also true
for the yes it's also true for the plus
sign you want to do it uh we can do
it
um let's just it's it's quite obvious
for Sigma 3 for Sigma 3 there's one up
electron and one down
electron uh no let's do it let's do it
why do I say that
um let's do it let's
do all right so we have to take the bra
Vector up down let's just write up down
plus which one did you say I did minus
okay so let's do plus uh plus uh down
up let's put a bracket around it or
squiggle around it and now let's take um
well let's first take Sigma
3 and then over here up down plus down
up no we got to write the the bracket
the other
way
and the square root of two doesn't
matter here if if it's zero it'll be
zero if we multiply it by square OT of
two or whatever okay so um what happens
if we multiply this by Sigma 3 Sigma 3
hits up and leaves it up Sigma 3 hits
down and changes the sign right so this
is just going to be um up down
minus down
up and I can leave out the sigma 3 now
because I've just acted with the sigma
3 times up
down plus down
up okay so the inner product of up
down with up down is one the inner
product of up down with down up is zero
they're different they're opposite uh so
right here we get a one from here and
then a minus one from here down up with
down up again is one but there's a minus
sign so we get
zero now this does not mean that these
states are igen vectors of Sigma 3 with
igen value zero it means the expectation
value of Sigma 3 is zero uh there's no
igen vectors of Sigma 3 with igen value
zero you can never get zero for one of
the spins you can only get plus or minus
one so it doesn't mean that when you
measure any of the spins you get zero
what it means is uh that uh that it's a
measuring the spin is a fair toin coin
toss where you get uh UPS as much as you
get Downs in equal amount equal
probability okay now
um I want to come to the difference and
the difference you can see most easily
by considering an operator which is the
sum of both spins in other words the
spins represent little vectors little
pointers excuse me little
pointers Sigma might point that
direction tow might point that direction
they represent little magnetic moments
we could think about the Magnetic Moment
of the combined system which is simply
the vector sum of the two uh the two
magnetic moments or the two
spins uh
and so it's interesting
then to look at the operator Sigma 1
Sigma plus to the very the three
components of it all three components of
it all right let's see what the
the let's see what Sigma plus to do to
these two states first of
all what is the action of Sigma
3 plus to
on up down plus down up oops up
down sorry plus minus down
up all right the answer is zero why is
that well first of all one reason is
obvious uh in up this the spin the third
component of Sigma 3 is up and down the
component of to 3 is down so they add up
to zero but let's just check it uh Sigma
3 acting on up gives plus
up uh to 3 acting on down gives minus so
Sigma 3 plus to 3 acting on up down will
give zero Sigma 3 acting on up gives
plus to 3 acting on down gives
minus and uh so Sigma 3 plus to 3
definitely equals zero for the leftand
state and also for the right hand one
over here so the conclusion is that
either of these states in fact just the
two separate components here are both
igen vectors of Sigma 3 plus to 3 with
igen value zero that means if you
measure Sigma 3 plus to 3 you will
always get zero okay for either of these
states that's not surprising since one
is up and one is down
okay now what about Sigma 1 plus to 1
let's do that little
exercise Sigma 1 plus to 1 this is the
sum of
the first component the the X component
of spin let's see if we can work out
what it does to up
down plus
minus down
up okay Let's uh start with Sigma 1 what
does Sigma 1 do to up it turns it down
right okay so Sigma one let's let's
write out everything that uh that comes
here Sigma one on up down gives
us down
down and sigma 1 and to one and up down
gives
minus to no sorry to one on down gives
up sorry so uh to one gives up up plus
up
up that's what we get by applying Sigma
1 plus to 1 to up down Sigma 1 flips up
down and makes down down to one flips
down up and makes up up with a plus sign
because with a plus no with a plus sign
the plus sign is this sign here
then we have plus or
minus okay then we have plus or minus
let's see what Sigma 1 does Sigma one
acts on down to give
up
up and
then plus
minus down
down
to one flips up down and gives you down
down okay the plus minus is the same
plus minus that's here
okay all right so it's quite clear that
if we take the plus sign we don't get
zero if we take the plus sign we don't
get zero we just get twice down
down plus twice up
up the implication is that if you were
to
measure uh well the implication is that
this is not an igen Vector of the sum of
Sigma 3 plus to 3 you will not get zero
every time you measure it even though
its expectation value happens to be zero
uh if you measure it sometimes you'll
get what are the possible values you can
get Sigma 3 can be plus or minus one to
3 can be plus or minus one so it's clear
the answer can be two zero or oh sorry
two Z or minus two is that right that's
all you can get right yeah but uh there
would be no reason and in fact it's
quite clear that you can't uh that that
you don't get zero every single time
because this is not an igen Vector of to
1 plus Sigma 1 with igen value zero so
uh we can be quite sure then that this
operator here doesn't not give zero
every time you measure it just because
it is not an igen when in this state
just because it's not an igen Vector
with igen value zero what about with a
minus sign with a minus sign in here
with a minus sign in here that means we
should put
minuses and the answer does
vanish down down minus down down up up
minus up up equals zero so the state
with a minus sign here let's concentrate
on that one now the state with a minus
one here every single time you measure
Sigma 1 plus to 1 you get zero every
single time you measure Sigma 3 plus to
3 there two separate electrons one of
them you measure Sigma the other one you
measure to you add the answers Sigma 1
plus to 1 or Sigma 2 plus to 2 or
whatever it is you measure you always
get zero for the sums of the third
components and for the sums of the first
components what about the second
component let's check that one one and I
won't do it for plus or minus now we've
already checked that Sigma 1+ to 1 does
not kill up down plus down up let's see
what happens if we put uh Sigma Sigma 2
plus to
2 on the same uh on the same Vector up
down
minus down
up all right first of all what does
Sigma 2 do Sigma 2 multiplies the up
here and makes it I times
down so the first entry will be I times
down
down that's from Sigma 2 time this now
what about to 2 * this to 2 gets uh
takes down and flips it up with a minus
I so that's minus I up
up now what about to 2 to 2 takes down
and flips it up with a minus I so that's
minus I down
down and then with a minus sign with
another minus sign
here to 2 takes up to down let's see am
I doing what I want to do
um where am I uh we already have two
down Downs how
to
which one am I trying to
do up up up that's T that's this one
yeah and that should be I * up
up plus I * up up so again it gives
zero all components of Sigma give zero
furthermore if I were to
take let's call it sigma. to it's a
little Vector Sigma Sigma plus to not
not that and dott it into some unit
Vector to take the component in any
direction well those things are built up
out of Sigma 1 plus to 1 Sigma 2 plus to
2 and sigma 3 plus to 3 so if we
basically we've checked that all three
components of Sigma plus to are zero and
therefore Sigma plus to in any direction
whatever Direction you measure it is in
you will get zero for the negative yeah
for the negative sign the negative sign
is called the singlet State why it's
called a singlet State maybe we'll get
to but for the moment it's called the
singlet
State and it has the property that the
sums of the little magnetic moments the
sums of the spins of the two particles
are exactly equal to zero every time you
measure it in any direction it happens
to have the property that it's
rotationally invariant no matter what
direction you measure it in it always
looks the same but we see that in
particular specifically from uh from
looking at the various components of
Sigma plus to they're all
zero
okay the implication of that of course
is that if you measure a component of
Sigma you'll instantly know what the
same component of cow is in other words
if we have an electron over there
Alice's electron over there and Bob's
electron over here and Bob measures any
component of the spin he instantly knows
what Alice will get if she measures the
same component of spin she won't he
won't necessarily know what uh what's
gotten by measuring some other component
of the spin but um what he does know is
if he measures any component of the spin
and gets an answer he instantly knows
what uh what Alice will get when she met
measures the other spin why because the
sums of the spins in any direction are
equal to
zero all right so that's a yeah what is
the same answer you mean literally the
same um one minus one plus one or on the
average will get the same every single
time every single
time and the reason is because this
Vector is an igen Vector of Sigma plus
to when it's an igen Vector that tells
you that every every time you measure it
in that state you get uh you get the
same answer equal to the igen value sing
what's that that's for the singlet State
for the singlet State yeah but not for
the the other one is called the triplet
State why another another issue will
come to another
day so the single state has the special
property that if you measure one spin
you automatically know that the other
one is in the opposite
direction okay meaning to say you know
you never measure the direction of a
spin you measure a component of the spin
any component of the spin that you
measure if you measure the same
component of the other spin you will get
the opposite answer okay so that's a
form of correlation it's kind of similar
to the penny and the
dime if uh if I uh if I give Alice one
coin and Bob the other coin Alice looks
at a coin she instantly knows what Bob
gets but it's somehow deeper than than
that it's not just uh the third
component the up down this but every
single
component uh whichever one you have you
happen to pick in any direction whatever
the two spins will come out to be
opposite okay that's a uh that's a
profound kind of
correlation that uh and it's called
Einstein Podolski Rosen
correlation where Einstein podowski and
Rosen the first ones to discover
entanglement no not at all
um I believe schinger first uh first
discussed it I think in fact I think he
called it entanglement and I think that
was
before but in any case let's uh let's go
on and I want to go
slowly I next want to come to Bell
famous
theorem I can tell you the theorem is
famous what I can't tell you is whether
or not it's profound but
trivial not Bell's theorem but Ben
Bell's inequality in the fact that
quantum mechanics violates it I cannot
tell you half the days of the week I
think this is the most profound thing
the in the world in the other half of
the days I say it's just a bit just
another consequence of quantum mechanics
what I can tell you is that John Bell
had exactly the same ambivalence to it
at least when I knew him uh and uh I can
tell you also that Richard fean had the
same ambivalence to it some of the times
it just seems so profound and so deep
and other times it just seems like well
it's a trivial consequence of quantum
mechanics of course it's true you'll
have to make up your own mind whether
you think it's very very profound or not
it gets a lot of press that it's the
most profound thing since swiss cheese
and some sometimes and you know it may
well be in the end it's going to depend
on what the consequences of it are for
future physics at the moment the
consequences are uh just quantum
mechanics works that's all and uh uh so
without further Ado Let's uh let's
discuss oh the theem itself is quite
trivial it probably
yeah excludes quantum mechanics the
theorem excludes quantum
mechanics no the theorem excludes
quantum
mechanics in quantum mechanics you can
find violations of Bell's
inequality Bell's inequality is an
absolutely
classical theorem it's a theorem about
classical systems completely classical
systems and when I derive it now I don't
want want you to remind me anything
about quantum mechanics because it
doesn't have to do with quantum
mechanics we're going to derive a
theorem about perfectly good classical
logic what is classical logic classical
logic is basically set
theory
um no no Paradox
yet I mean so far we just does that
clown cality is that a Sear issue no it
would violate causality if you could use
it to send a message if by Bob looking
at the spin Alice with to instantly know
something that she didn't know before
that would violate causality but she
doesn't she doesn't know anything
different uh than
uh uh she has no more information than
she had before for example if in this
state her spin half the time will be up
and half the time will be down
that'll be true Bob May measure his spin
she doesn't know anything she'll look at
her spin half the times it'll be up half
the times it'll be down if she gets a
message from Bob and the message says my
spin is up then she knows that her spin
is down but she's got to get that
message and that message can't uh can't
uh be gotten faster than the speed of
light are there any time any inertial
time time frames for one is in front of
the other
[Music]
measures first
me no no no no whatever whatever Bob
does whatever Bob does if Alice doesn't
get a message from Bob that she doesn't
get a message from Bob there are no
implications for anything for her she'll
still she will have learned nothing from
the fact that Bob made the
measurement uh she'll know nothing she
has to get a message from him to use the
information that he has if he sends her
a message I got up then she knows it's
down but
uh uh
but without that message being sent she
doesn't know anything new so this is in
no way a violation of causality locality
or anything like
that that's one of the reasons that half
the days of the week I think this isn't
so profound it doesn't violate anything
deep or important in uh in uh uh in
um we view the singet state is when you
have the U minus sign and the igen
values are plus or minus two or
zero well no if you measure Sigma plus
to in the sing State you get zero okay
any direction any component it's in the
triplet state which is the one with a
plus where if you measure it you can get
uh uh two Z
or or minus one or minus two excuse
me okay so let me tell you what Bell's
theorem is it's a very simple theorem
supposing we have some objects all a
collection of
them uh a set of
things and we look at the class of the
objects that have certain properties and
I'm going to consider three properties
I'm going to call them A B and C
whatever they happen to be uh they could
stand for anything any properties uh a b
and
c let me write down the inequality
first in other words each one of these
little things whatever it is here's some
set here's some
set and each member of the set has an a
a b and a c it has a it has these
properties all right now we can I'm
interested in the
number of
entities which have property
a and not
b not B is whatever the opposite of b is
all right
so whatever whatever the opposite of B
is the number of things which have
property a and not B plus the number of
things that have property B and not
C and the classical theorem which is so
easy that I I've never understood why
there are long long winded proofs of it
it's a it's it's basically very
Elementary is greater than or equal to
the number of things with property a and
not C okay the number of things with a
and not B plus the number of things with
b and not C is greater than or equal to
the number of things with a and not C
how do you prove this you prove it by
drawing
pictures uh for one reason or another in
all the literature that I can find they
never draw a picture it's uh all right
let's draw the St the uh the um the set
or let's delineate the set which has
property a the subset which has property
a here's the subset which has property
a well let me do it the way I have it in
my notes so I don't uh so I don't screw
up
yeah all right here's a over here let's
go a now then where is the subset B the
subset B may or may not intersect a all
right if it intersects a it means they
have elements in common if it doesn't
intersect a it means they don't have
elements in common but here's the subset
B and if B has no elements in common
with a it just means you should move it
just means that this region over here is
zero that there's no uh that uh that
there's nothing in here all right but in
general there'll be something in here
which will be those things which have
both A and
B and finally C here's
C now again C may or may not have
elements in common with a or b if it
doesn't you just move it out of you just
move it over a little bit so that it
doesn't have elements in common with A
and C but the most General situation is
where it does have elements in common
but you could can always you lose
Nothing by pretending it has elements in
common because you can always at the end
say that the elements in common are just
a null set there are just none of them
okay now let's let's oh and let's also
label put the put some color in here
let's also label all these various
individual little sub regions here let's
see what I call
them okay this region out here is just
one what is that that's all of a which
is neither B nor
C and I'm just going to label all the
various sub areas in here
three
five 6 and seven and of course there may
be some elements which have neither a b
or c and they'll be out here but I don't
even need to rep to to write those down
because I'm not interested in
them okay let's take the number of
elements that have a and not b that has
a but does not have B what is that
that's region one and
two if it has a but it doesn't have B
that means it's a but exclude anything
that has B and that means that it's the
number that's in one plus the number
that's in two everybody see
that okay so the first thing here is
N1 plus N2
that's NA a not b now what about the
number of the number of systems which
has B but not C so we go over to B and
we ask and we exclude those that have
C five and six have
C so in looking at
B the things which have B but not C what
are those that's plus things which have
B but not C
four and seven right plus N4 plus
N7 now what about n and not uh what
about a and not C A and not C is one and
four a and not C is one and
four did I get that right sorry what I
want to write here is is greater than
equal
to no what did I I wrote something
wrong a and not
C say it
again this one and which one which one
in
and7
right do I have it right I think so yes
all right well obviously this is here's
N1 here's
N4 obviously N1 and all the ns are
positive I mean there's no such thing as
negative number of elements right N1
plus N2 plus N4 plus N7 is certainly
bigger than N1 plus N4 or or equal to it
at worst it's equal to
it that's Bell's theorem that's the
whole thing that's
it what's amazing is that it's violated
it can be
[Laughter]
violated the violation is profound yeah
but all of quantum mechanics violate
classical music so I
mean
yeah
I as I said I've always been ambivalent
and I'm not I'm never going to get
unambivalent about it I'll die being
ambivalent to it so you get State
yourself when you think
about that's what that's when I start
thinking it's profound
yeah
okay let's now take our system to be two
spins
let's take our system to V2 spins and
then we'll Define the various properties
A and
B uh a b and
c which we'll think of incidentally
we're still doing we're doing we're
imagining Let's see we well
yeah we we'll first
pretend that the spins are classical and
that you can measure
them as if they were classical objects
and we'll write down what Bell's
inequality says for the system of two
spins the only thing you need to know
and you have to keep track of I'm going
to talk about spin one I'm only going to
talk about spin
one but what I'm going to say is we're
going to say things like here here might
be a proposition a proposition might be
that spin one let's see I guess uh how
did I label
this spin one is
up
along
z-axis along the third axis that could
be some
proposition well I can the negative of
it is spin one is not up along the third
axis but of course that's the same as
saying it's down along the third axis
but if spin one is measured down along
the third axis then you can be sure that
two is up along the third axis so the
negative in the single state in the
singlet State we're putting the
electrons into the singlet State all
right and if classical logic if ordinary
logic made any sense here's what we
would do we would measure we we have a
whole beam of these of these electron
pairs zillions of them zillions of pairs
which are each correlated in this
fashion separate from each other and you
measure the first 100,000 of them in
every possible Direction you measure
Sigma 1 and to 1 you measure Sigma 3 and
to 3 for many many of them and you
convince yourself after a long tedious
bunch of experiments that every time you
measure a component of this Spin and you
measure a component of the same the same
component of the other spin that they're
always opposite to each other in that
case I think we would all
agree that the negative of saying or the
opposite of saying a is up is saying
that b is up because if a is down then B
is up right so the negative of a
proposition about one
spin becomes the positive statement
about the other spin the negative of
spin one being spin what do it call ao1
I forgot uh the negative of calling this
spin the negative of this spin being up
is the spin down but then it's the same
as saying that the spin is up okay so we
just have to keep keep track of what uh
of the relationship between these
various
propositions okay we're going to write
down what a B and C
are
a and we're only going to talk about
spin one at first but then we're going
to use spin
two to tell us something about spin one
all right so a
is
up along
three axis that's
a okay
B this equal sign here just means is the
statement is the statement that spin one
is up along the third
axis
B is that spin one is up along a 45
degree
angle
the 45 degree angle could be in the um
in the ZX plane in the ZX plane for
example let's take it to be in the ZX
plane so B says spin one is up along the
45 degree angle in the ZX plane and
C says that one is
up
along the 90° Direction in the X Y in
the uh zy ZX plane okay so here's our
picture a says that the spin is up along
the third axis
B says that it's lies at 45° along the
uh uh along the 40 along that axis and C
says that it lies at 90 Dees along that
axis a b
c
okay now what about not
B let's take not well first of all let's
take not a I don't think we need not a
for anything we will need not b not
B says that one does not
lie uh that the spin is not up along the
45° axis it says it's down along the 45
degre axis but then it says that spin
two is up along the
45° all right so not B is that that spin
two is up along
45° not
b b is that one is up along the 45
degree not B is the two is up along the
45 Dee okay you get the idea same thing
for c not
C is that
two is up along
90°
okay so now we can plug into here what
this various statements
say
no not C let's see C says that one is up
along the 90 not C says one is down
along the 90 but
then two is up okay so whatever the
statement is the notot of the statement
is the original statement except made on
the other spin okay is that clear the
other spin is in the opposite direction
that's all it says so whatever a not
statement is it becomes a yes statement
about the other
spin okay so let's write down what this
says all right this says the number of
pairs the entities now are pairs of
electrons pairs of
electrons uh this becomes then
the number
of
pairs with spin up let's call it
um spin one is up
along up at 0
degrees
up at 0
degrees and the other spin Let's see we
want not b not B is that the other spin
is up along the 45° angle all right so
the Second Spin this is the first spin
here I'm writing in the Second Spin
up along
45° right
a is that spin one is up along the third
axis and not B is that spin two is up
along 45
degrees
h
yeah this stands for this stands for
electron one this stands for electron
two okay the first entry here is
electron one the second entry here is
electron
2 next B not C now I don't have to worry
about B not C and I'll tell you why it's
got to be exactly the same as a not b
why is that um b a not
b and b not C are simply related by
rotating by uh by by
45° anything I can say about a and not B
will be exactly the same as B and not C
because they're identical to each other
except for a rotation by
45° okay and uh the singlet State
doesn't change if you rotate it by 45
degrees that's that's the main thing
about it it doesn't change when you
rotate we saw that by seeing that the
spin total spin is the same in every
direction so in fact uh we can just take
this to be
twice the sum of this and this are just
twice the number of up at 0 degrees and
down at 45 degrees and Bill's theorem if
it were true would tell us that this is
greater than necessarily greater than
greater than or
equal to the number
of pairs with the property that they're
up
uh this should be C should be um I write
C
correctly
yeah yeah C is up along
90° um right a is one up along three
along zero what's that along the
zis yeah okay so right a is one is up at
degrees and not c means two is up along
90° two is up at 90
de well now we have something we can
test incidentally counting the number of
them is the same as counting the
probability for these things to be true
if we have a large number of identical
things in an ensemble measuring the
number is just measuring the probability
okay if we have 100,000 uh pairs the
number which has a certain property is
just a certain percentage of 100,000
which is given the percentage is given
by the
probability okay so here's the question
then in the singlet State what is the
probability what are these various
probabilities the probability for uh for
first electron to be up at 0 degrees and
the second electron to be up at 45° how
do we calculate that all right I want to
here's a question I'm going to tell you
the answer right now the answer right
now is that this is less than this when
you calculate it we're going to
calculate it but this is less than this
and it simply
violates the very very Elementary
theorem that uh that B it's hardly a
theorem it's just a very simple
observation about
probabilities okay um
let's see if we can calculate these
things what I need to do in order to
calculate them
efficiently is to teach you about
projection
operators so let me tell you what a
projection operator is and let me give
you an alternative definition of the
probability uh postulate of quantum
mechanics a projection
operator
it's labeled like that projection
operator P for projection operator has a
number of properties but first I'm going
to tell you what it give you a picture
of what it does what it would do in an
ordinary projection operator in
three-dimensional space if my Vector
space happened to be just vectors in
three
dimensions then there are subspaces a
Subspace of three-dimensional space
could be Zero Dimensional that's just a
point just the origin nothing at all it
could be a one-dimensional Subspace
which is just a line sticking out of the
origin or a two-dimensional Subspace
which is a plane passing through the
origin um if you like it's the space
which is well you get it you if you have
a pair a two-dimensional Vector space
would be take any pair of
vectors and think of all the vectors
that you can make by adding these two
with arbitrary coefficients all those
vectors will lie in the plane of those
two vectors that's the Subspace which is
spanned by two vectors if I have only
one vector and I want that's a
one-dimensional Subspace then it's all
the vectors that lie along a line if you
have a higher dimensional Subspace then
uh I'm sorry a higher dimensional space
then you can have subspaces up to the
dimensionality of one less than the uh
than the space itself all right what is
a projection operator a projection
operator in particular a projection
operator onto a one-dimensional space in
particular it's an operation which takes
any
vector and takes its
projection onto that
Subspace and gives you the vector which
is the projection along the
Subspace uh of the original Vector it's
an operator so it will operate on a
vector it's called Alpha to give you the
projection it's called Alpha sub P onto
the appropriate Subspace if the Subspace
is this line here then it would act on
any Vector to give you the projection
onto that
Subspace
okay so that's what it does it takes
away it removes the components of a
vector in directions perpendicular to
the Subspace it just chops them out and
removes them okay um
let's see how about projection onto a
two-dimensional Subspace a simple
two-dimensional Subspace would just be
let's say the uh XY plane just the XY
plane here would be a two-dimensional
Subspace if I have an arbitrary Vector
then it just projects onto the plane and
gives you the projection onto the
plane okay that's the notion of a
projection
operator now suppose we have some
properties that we're interested
in the property is let's take the
property to be the spin is up along the
third axis there's an igen Vector that
goes with that the up igen Vector along
the third
axis therefore there's a projection
operator that goes with that statement
the statement that the spin is up along
the x-axis corresponds to a projection
operator it's the projection operator
which projects onto the I Vector in
which the spin is up along the third
axis okay so what does it do it takes
any
state the projection operator that
projects onto spin being up for one spin
let's just talk about one spin what is
that it's an operator which takes any
Vector let's call it Alpha
Beta And what does it give this is
projection onto Sigma 3 = 1 projection
onto Sigma 3al one what does it
give how high it
is how high it is where it intersects
the what the vertical
axis no it just throws away
Thea it just throws it
away beta is orthogonal the state with
the lower entry here is orthogonal to
the state in which the spin is up
okay so all it does is it picks out the
component of the vector along the
particular uh property that you're
interested in right so it just gives you
Alpha
zero it throws away the piece of the
vector that has to do with spin being
down what uh what does P3 equal minus
sorry P3 P Sigma 3 = minus1 do on the
same
Vector it throws away
Alpha all right here's an alternative
formulation what's
that Sigma 3us one excuse
me incidentally p is an operator it
operates on a vector to give a new
Vector there must be a matrix that goes
with it let me tell you what the Matrix
is
okay the projection operator onto Sigma
3 =
+1 that's the Matrix
one0
0 let's check that suppose that acts on
Alpha
Beta what does it give it gives 1 time
Alpha and zero times
beta 0o Time beta okay so that's
true there's another way to write it
which is going to be very efficient and
we're going to find it very very useful
to write this operator in the form Sigma
3 + 1 /
2 let's check that Sigma
3 is 1 - 1 0
0 + 1 which is 1 1 0
0 the one place the lower element here
vanishes minus one + one and then divide
by two okay so in the upper entry here
you get 1+ 1 is two divided by two
that's one and every place else you get
zero right this is a useful fact that
the projection operator onto a
configuration where the third component
of spin is
plus is just Sigma 3 + 1 /
2 what about things like Sig one or Sig
2 what said what what about projections
corresponding to Sigma one or Sigma yeah
okay so now let's ask that question what
would you expect the answer to be if I
asked you what's the projection operator
that projects onto the igen vector Sigma
1 equal + 1
1+ 1 two
exactly this is projection operator for
let's just call it projection operator
for Sigma
3 here's projection operator for Sigma
1 and by that I mean that Sigma 1 is
equal to + one that's just equal to
Sigma 1 + 1 / 2 you can check that easy
to check it's very easy to check that's
the projection
operator so let me give you now an
alternative definition
of the probability um postulate of
quantum
mechanics if you have a state an
arbitrary
State let's call it
s and you're interested in the
probability that a certain thing is
true or then you measure it that a
certain thing is true you construct the
projection operator for that certain
thing you call it
P the expect ation value of the
projection operator is the probability
for that thing probability for Alpha
let's let's just check that for for a
simple
case supposing again s is just uh Alpha
Beta it's just a vector Alpha
Beta and P3 is Sigma 3 + 1 okay so here
we have Alpha
Beta we have Sigma 3 + 1 1 / 2 and then
we have Alpha star beta star this is the
expectation value of the projection
operator what do we get well what does
Sigma 3 do on this Vector
here it multiplies the alpha by 1 and
the beta by minus one right so what it
gives when Sigma 3 plus a half Sigma 3 +
1 / by two acts on this Vector here it
just gives something simple Sigma 3 + 1
/ two gives + one on
Alpha and what does it give it gives
zero on beta right just gives zero it
just we already know what it does it
just gives this times Alpha star beta
star this is just equal to Alpha star
Alpha so there's an example where
calculating the expectation value of a
projection operator gives you the
probability in this case for the spin to
be
up so this is an alternative definition
of the probability assumption if you're
interested in a certain proposition
Alpha is true you construct the
projection operator for
Alpha in the way that I showed you it's
the projection operator onto the
direction which is the igen vector
corresponding to the proposition and
then you just calculate its expectation
value that gives you the probability
okay very simple an alternative uh an
alternative rout to getting the pro the
probabilities all right so now we have
everything we need to calculate the
various probabilities that are in this
expression here should I stop from let
me let's stop for a little bit let's
stop for a little bit probably getting a
headache by now okay look let me let me
simplify what I said down to its Bare
Essentials projection
operators correspond to statements well
let me go back a step classical physics
statements are subsets properties are
subsets of a uh of a set the set of all
things we start with the set of all
things the set of all things such that
that's a subset the basic ideas of
intersection and Union and all those
kind of things about sets and subsets
are classical logic that's what
classical logic is about the classical
logic of ver of propositions
propositions mean properties properties
of systems in
physics uh in quantum mechanics a very
very different setup propositions do not
correspond to
subsets they correspond to subspaces of
a vector space subspaces of a vector
space are a very different thing than
subsets of a
set and therein lies the very big
differences and therein we're going to
see allows us to C calculate the well
we're going to use the fact that
properties correspond to projection
operators um or or you can say that they
correspond to the subspaces the Subspace
of states which has this or that
property and for our purposes
now the only projection operators that
I'm going to be interested in are the
ones which correspond to spin in a given
Direction being
up okay so let's
okay the projection operator
for Let's uh start with where's where's
our anybody remember what a b and c were
I don't oh yes here it is all right a
was the first spin is up along the third
axis all right what's the projection
operator for
this it's Sigma
3 + one 1
/
two that's only half the statement
though the Second Spin is up along the
45 degree axis all right what uh what is
the projection operator for that anybody
know the 45 degree axis what's the spin
what's the component of spin along the
45 degree axis first of
all I don't
know it's something like to 1 plus to 3
right I mean it's along an axis is
halfway between 1 and
three so that's to 1 plus to 3 but
that's not quite right what's wrong with
it normal one over theun of
two here's what we're doing we're taking
um n the unit Vector along
45° and dotting it into toao all right
what's uh the uh what the components of
n along 45° they're one over the < TK of
two so this is uh to 1 over the < TK of
two plus to 3 over the < TK of two
that's the component of to along 45°
axis all right so it's uh the projection
operator for
um uh
for the second statement here is to 1
plus to 3
plus over the < TK of
two +
one what I'm using is that the
projection operator for sigma.
n is just sigma. n the projection
operator is sigma. n + 1 /
2 that projects you onto the Subspace in
which sigma. n is +
one uh yeah whole thing has to be
divided by two thank you thank
you good okay
now if you apply both projection
operators to a state this one acts on
the first Spin and projects the state
onto the component or it acts only on
the first Spin and takes away anything
in which Sigma do3 is in the wrong
direction and then if you act with this
one second it takes away anything on the
Second Spin which is in the wrong
direction so the whole projection
operator that corresponds to this
combined
statement that uh that the first spin is
up along the 0 degrees the Second Spin
is up along 45 degrees is just the
product of these two you act first with
one of them that throws away everything
in the state Vector that's in the wrong
uh in the wrong direction in the space
of states and then you act with the
other one that throws away everything
that's in the wrong Direction
corresponding to the other spin so the
product of these two is the projection
operator that projects out or that
projects for you up along 0 degrees for
the first Spin and up along 45 degre for
the Second
Spin and remember that's a and not b not
B
Because B you remember B corresponds to
up along uh up along the 45 5° axis not
B corresponds to down along the 45° axis
but then we look at particle 2 instead
of particle one and particle one always
has the opposite spin so it becomes up
along the 45 degree axis for spin number
two this is the projection operator for
this object for this property over here
for the property that a and not
B okay all right its expectation value
in the singlet state corresponds to the
uh to the
probability for a and not B all right so
all we can do there's only one way to do
this and that's to just hold your breath
and start writing and working out the
details one by one I'm going to do it
this is tedious
it's it may bore you you can close your
eyes and I'll tell you what the answer
is but you might as well see how it's
done for those who are really interested
for those who aren't interested no
that's you can go home
okay so let's write down the singlet
State here the singlet state is up
down minus down up and now we better put
in the square root of
two now later on we're going to take the
inner product of what we have and
project it back onto the same Vector so
later on we're going to project back on
to the
singlet all right but for now I just
want to calculate what this operator
does does when it hits the
state okay it's actually not too bad um
first of all what does Sigma 3 + 1 do to
this over
here yeah it just throws this
away why because in this state here the
first spin is down but this is the
projection operator onto the first spin
being up so when Sigma 3 + 1 / two
acts on a state where the first spin is
down it just kills it so we might as
well get rid of
that okay and now we've done it we've
used sigma 3 + 1 over two so we can uh
we can now rewrite this I won't erase it
but I'll write it we can get rid of this
we've acted with it and it just kills
the second uh the second entry yeah the
rest of it is to 1 + to 3 over 2 < tk2 +
1 12 half all acting on 1 over the < TK
of two let's put one over another one
over < TK of two out
here that's this one and then that acts
on up
down okay what does it
do um first of all what does to one do
to
one flips now remember tows act on the
second entry to one flips down to up so
when toan acts it gives up up
here okay what's in here is there
anything with up up in
here no no nothing with up up in here
all there is is up down and down up so
that means when to one acts it gives
something which is completely orthogonal
to what's on the left hand side it won't
contribute when we take the inner
product with a Signet when to one occurs
and acts on down to give up it'll give
something on the right hand side that
just doesn't appear in the corresponding
bra Vector so we can be quite sure then
that to one will have no expectation
will just not
contribute uh to this uh to this inner
product I can throw it
away what does to 3 do to
this
down three
down is it minus down minus yeah to
three remember to acts on the second
entry here to 3 measures the component
of the Second Spin and the Second Spin
is down so that's just minus one when it
acts on down it just gives minus one it
just multiplies it by minus one so this
just becomes minus
one
that's it just a number the whole effect
of all of this stuff here is to throw
away the second state that's Sigma 3 + 1
and the and the tow operation here just
gives this number now that's not quite
true there's another piece there's the
up up piece but the up up piece will not
have anything to uh to take it in
product
with all right let's write down the
singlet State on this side the singlet
State on this side is up down minus down
up
/ by square < TK of
two well the down up configuration won't
contribute it's orthogonal to up down
down up is orthogonal to up down so this
one will not contribute we can get rid
of
it the inner product of up down with
itself is just
one so the whole thing is just given by
these numbers 1/ > of two 1 /un of two
and this Beast over
here this is the
probability for a and not B so what is
it one over of two it's
12 12 - 1 over 2 >
2 anybody can do numbers quick in their
head
um 1
two yeah
1/4 of what do you have 1 - 1/ of
two is that
right all right 1 over two is about
7 7
right 1 minus 1/ square 1/ square otk of
two is 1.4 1 over 1.4 is about
7 1 - 7
is.3 so this is. 3 over 4 how big is
that
0075 0075
right but
remember that we have
twice that this one and this one are
equal and so we have twice that so this
number here is
twice 0075 which is what point uh uh 75
and 75 is 150 Point uh
0.15
015 nice and
small now let's calculate this one okay
this is all right I we'll do we'll just
do it on the same on the same
construction here all right we still
have one we still have electron one up
along the zero axis that's
this but now we have electron 2 is up
along
90° 90° means the one axis the
projection operator for the one axis is
just to one over to 1 + 1 over
two now I'm not going to erase this I'm
just going to uh I'm just going to uh um
doctor it up so that it corresponds to
the second statement over here so let's
see so we can get rid of the to
3 it's just to 1 / 2 plus a half that's
it okay let's
uh okay again Sigma 3 + 1 /2 again gets
rid of this term here it picks out the
component of the state in which the
first spin is up so nothing new as far
as that's
concerned and now let's see what to one
one does to one takes up down to up so
when to one acts it makes up up but
there's no up up on this side here so
this one doesn't contribute at all let's
see this is not minus this is just plus
plus a half all right so the town one
doesn't give anything either Town one
acting on down gives up you have up up
here but you have no up up over here so
that's dead and all you get is 1
half this is it
Sigma 3 + 1 did nothing all you got
was2 and now you got some square roots
of two you have a square root of two
from here and you have a square root of
two from here so the whole thing is one
qu
0.25 this thing here is
0.25 well 1 0.15 is not bigger than 0.25
we went through this whole exercise to
see that the right hand side here is
bigger than the left hand side this is
what John Bell did course I know it's
the only thing he did in physics but uh
it's pretty brilliant um the little
exercise in quantum mechanics here is
one you can go home and redo for
yourself but the upshot is that uh that
the quantum singlet state of a pair of
electrons violates uh Bell's theorem
Bell's in equality what does that mean
that means
that there there is no
possibility that there's an underlying
classical underlying classical um way of
thinking about quantum mechanics where
properties are somehow um governed by
ordinary set theory there's no possible
underlying description of classical
under underlying description of quantum
mechanics it cannot be the statistic
iCal theory of some
complicated um chaotic jumbled classical
system so you don't need to do any
experiments if you already have quantum
mechanics and then you know BS
inequality is not going to not going to
work you know need to do those
experiments absolutely so aspect what
same is did all experiments or
nothing uh well the question is whether
or not nature follows quantum mechanics
no no no no everybody knew that nature
follows quantum mechanics I mean you
know quantum mechanics have been tested
to very high Precision let's put it this
way um
well it's a beautiful experiment I'm
sure it was fun to do did it teach us
anything we didn't know well it might
have taught us something about the
technology of manipulating electrons and
I suspect it did and I suspect it was a
hard experiment
uh it was very delicate experiment and
so it probably is part of the March
toward being able to manipulate small
things I think in that sense it was a a
piece of
technology was the result certain
beforehand absolutely I mean you
know yeah I mean no the experiment the
experiment could not have those quantum
mechanics have been checked in so many
ways before that that uh that uh nobody
expected did now I'll tell you what
aspect it do which is a hard thing to do
it's a hard thing to do what it
checked here's here's what you would
want to check okay is there an out is
there an out is there any way that
classical logic could somehow simulate
quantum mechanics the answer is yes but
only if the system that you're talking
about sort of has wires connected of the
left electron to the right electron in
some way that makes the the experiment
on the left not not independent of the
experiment on the on the right if you
had somehow that when you did the
experiment over here some signal went
over here and told it to rearrange and
do something complicated in other words
if you have a whole bunch of wires
coming from the left and the right and
they join together and you have a
processor in the center you can simulate
quantum mechanics but it's at the cost
that signals have to be able to go
faster than the speed of light the that
if you had any any classical system that
could somehow detect what you did over
here and send the message quickly over
to there instantly before the second
experiment or in other words if Bob
could send a message to Alice
instantly and uh and tell her what's
going on yes there are ways to uh to
simulate uh quantum mechanics
classically so the second element of
this is that the experiments on the left
and the right that measure the two
components of spin really are
independent that they're far from each
other and couldn't have interfered with
each other now one way of making
absolutely certain that they couldn't
have interfered with each other is to
make all of Alice's experiments take
place right at the basically at the same
time or very very shortly after Bob's
experiments if Alice's experiment takes
place at a time for which light could
not have traveled from Bob then Alice's
experiment must be independent no wire
could have sent a piece of information
there would be no way that any classical
uh classical signal could have been sent
from one to the other so one of the
things that was in aspect experiment was
not just that taking these singlet
electrons and measuring them and so
forth the left one and the right one and
uh and checking whether uh whether the
inequality was satisfied but he managed
to do it in such a way that there was no
ambiguity that Alice's electron was
measured sufficiently soon after Bob's
electron that light could not have
propagated between them that was the
hard part of the experiment as far as I
know to be able to uh to be able to
um uh do both experiments sufficiently
simultaneously that there was no
possibility of information flow
classical information flow from one to
the other so the two experiments of uh
Alice and Barb were in that
sense uh independent of each other under
the assumption that no signals can
travel faster than the speed of
light um all attempts to simulate
quantum mechanics from classical
underlying logic always make use of some
non-local assumptions some kind of thing
which uh can process signals at one end
and send them to the other end uh
essentially
instantaneously so I think that was the
hard part of Alan aspec's experiment was
the timing issue I
think and I think that was the sort of
technological Triumph that they were
able to be quite certain that the second
experiment was done within the transit
time of a light beam from the first
experiment uh no interference between
them yeah uh didn't Belle do this after
Einstein died oh I suppose yeah like so
but Einstein he he and what did what did
Bell do that that clarified this this
this uh he just made a very
quantitative statement a very
quantitative statement uh you know
Einstein had this idea somehow this is
uh this is funny well what was spooky
what was spooky about it this is what
was spooky about it that it violated a
uh a classical logic proposition
now it's not surprising that you can
violate classical logic propositions
quantum mechanics is not classical logic
but he just pinned one down he just
pinned one down very very solidly and uh
was very quantitative about it uh the
fact that the experiment was done was
probably less important than he put his
finger on a thought experiment that
could be done which would if it were
done would rule out a classical underl
basis he didn't have to do the
experiment he said no this this is
enough this is enough I know that
quantum mechanics will work for this and
therefore I know that quantum mechanics
cannot have an underlying classical
basis uh he was very ambivalent about
all of this I mean some of the times he
thought this was brilliant some of the
times he thought that it's trivial and
toward the end of his life he started to
qu he thought it was so brilliant that
he began to question quantum mechanics
and uh began to question whether quantum
mechanics uh was the Right theory but uh
yeah this isn't a
question may you can comment on it
usually you think quantum mechanics is
really tiny things but here you got two
electrons that are flying part it could
be miles apart yeah and it still have a
common W function yeah so now it's it's
really large thing you're talking about
well it's small things far apart I
mean you couldn't do it with two bowling
balls let's put it that
way but your point is is well taken but
but I mean you still it's still about
small things but the small things you
have to be careful to keep the quantum
wave function intact when you take
things
apart when you take things apart
disturbing influences can ruin the wave
function for example just the
atmosphere interacting with the
atmosphere can do things to the wave
function that ruin the experiment so
when you take them apart it's very
delicate you better do it in a vacuum
you better do it cold you better make
sure that there's no photons around that
can interact with the electrons and uh
and Care is required and the further you
take them apart the more care that's
going to be required because the quantum
wave function tends to get out of sync
not by itself but by interaction with
other things interaction with an
environment we'll I think we'll try to
talk a little about interaction with an
environment uh wasn't the idea that U
you could measure something about that
second electron just by looking at the
first one right and and so therefore
Heisenberg's uncertainly
principle the way I think Heisenberg
understood it wouldn't be valid well no
I
mean this is a trick which makes it look
like you violating Heisenberg's
uncertainty principle but it is still
true that you cannot directly measure uh
certain simultaneous properties about
one electron you really haven't done
that you've uh you can measure the
position of one of them and
veloc yeah nobody's going to stop you
from doing that you can do that uh but
uh it's not quite the same thing as
measuring the position and velocity of
one
electron
uh and in fact I mean there's a theorem
that you really can't make a machine
that will replicate uh uh that will
replicate the a Quantum system with
another one just like it fact we could
prove that theem right now if we want to
do it in a minute well should we do the
no cloning
theorem minut yeah in your argument you
use the product of two projections to
simulate the end of two
propositions so does that mean that the
product oh yeah yeah okay all right yeah
yeah yeah yeah I wanted to come to that
I forgot about that yeah okay um when
two propositions are independent of each
other now what does that mean that means
that you can measure both of them
simultaneously it means that the it
means that the projection operators
commute with each other if you have two
commuting projection operators then the
and statement means something um a
projection for example what doesn't mean
something would be to say if you only
had one electron if you had one electron
you could ask what's the probability
that the spin is both up along the uh
along the third axis and up along the
the second axis all right that would be
a meaningless question you can't you
can't do that because the third
component the two components of spin
don't commute with each other if you
multiply them take the two projection
operators one of them is 1 plus uh plus
Sigma 3 over two and the other is 1 +
Sigma 1 over two
right
is that the way to write it or should I
put them in the other order you get
different answer so um there's no
meaningful and for the spin is up along
the third axis and the spin is up along
the first axis right that uh that's a
forbidden kind of
and but here we're talking about two
different electrons and all of the
operators for one electron commute with
all the operators of the other electron
doesn't matter matter which order you
apply Sigma and toao that's because
Sigma acts on one of them and Tao acts
on the other one and they completely
commute they're completely independent
uh measurements they don't interfere
with each other measuring one spin
doesn't really do anything to the other
one so particularly if they're far apart
so yes that's something I should have
stressed yes the product is the and
operation but it only makes sense if the
two projection operators or if the two
properties are are
compatible if the two properties are
compatible which means they commute with
each other then the product is the end
is that was your question yeah okay good
good
point uh
yeah um one way I heard this
describe in terms of the measurement of
one particle imposes a constraint or
partial wave function CSE okay well yeah
do you feel that's a helpful way of
looking at it or well I don't know it's
particularly a helpful way of looking at
B theorem and so forth but uh
but um that's what I wanted to come to I
wanted to come either to the no cloning
theorem
or the measurement process and the
collapse of the wave packet or the
collapse of the wave function as being a
special case of
entanglement uh which one should we do I
think I think we have I think we're
better off today doing the no cloning
theorem and then next time we'll talk
about the measurement process as a
process of
entanglement entanglement of what with
what the apparatus getting entangled
with the system that you're
measuring that's what happens when you
do an experiment when you do an
experiment you have a you have you may
have a you know a dial not a dial a
pointer that tells you if it goes this
way the spin was up if it goes that way
the spin was down you take your electron
and you put it into the apparatus and if
the electron is up then the poter points
this way if the electron is down then
the poter points this way sounds like
entanglement sounds like entanglement
between the apparatus and the electron
and it is that's what the measurement is
but we'll come to that uh I I want to
prove a little theorem for
you um we're going to have to introduce
some additional
things
we have not talked about how State
vectors change with time we're going to
talk about that next time I
think but I'm going to tell you one fact
about about the time
evolution of wave functions namely it's
linear what does that mean that means if
you start with a wave function
a and under time or under some process
under some process it transforms into
wave function let's say a
prime and if we start with a wave
function b a different one and it goes
to B
Prime then if you start with the wave
function Alpha
a plus beta
B in time it will go to the same linear
combination of a
prime
that's a postulate of quantum mechanics
which is certainly experimentally
extremely well tested and what it says
is that the wave
function the the uh the state Vector of
a system changes in time linearly
linearly means that superp positions of
States transform into Super positions of
States uh in a linear way that's a
postulate of Quant mechanics which is
experimentally known to be true to
extremely high accuracy it's linearity
of quantum mechanics so let me show you
what it
says uh about trying to clone
systems here's our goal here's the goal
of
cloning supposing I have a system in any
old Quantum State whatever I want the
machine that I can feed it into and that
machine will spit out two copies two
identical copies
each in the same way function that the
original one system started with so it's
a cloning operation and in particular
for
example in fact whatever the initial
state of the system is it should produce
two systems in The Identical State
that's the
cloning um goal to be able to to be able
to clone Quantum
systems now classical cloning is
possible
the Xerox machine classically clones
information on a piece of paper it
doesn't do it exactly Faithfully because
little errors happen and so forth but
the degree of error can be controlled
and so you can clone classical systems
you can build machines that whatever
state on that piece of paper you put
into it it will produce two pieces of
paper with identical information all
right uh the I actually rediscovered the
no cloning theorem a long time ago and
called it the no no Xerox principle and
string theorists call it the no Xerox
principle no Quantum Xerox principle all
right so here's all you have to do is
prove it for one system because if I can
prove that I can't if I want to prove
that that that I can't clone everything
then all I have to do is show I can't
clone one thing so I'll show you what
you can't clone right right here's
here's my cloning apparatus here's a it
has a port over here that you put stuff
into and it has two ports over here that
you take stuff out of all right so in
goes one in in goes your system and out
comes two identical copies all right
let's start with an up electron
supposing we start with an up electron
so we start with one electron in the UP
State let's just call it up up what do
we get out we get out two
ups up up I mean by assumption by
assumption all right so we can say then
that the up the single electron state
evolves in time into a two electron
State how it does
this nobody knows incidentally that
violates charge conservation so let's
make it
neutrons uh H what
Mass no no no no no no no no no no no no
you don't that that means energy
conservation but energy doesn't have to
be conserved it can borrow energy from
the from the machine it can borrow
energy from the machine okay but it
would violate charge conservation unless
you get charge from the machine and
that's okay there's nothing wrong with
that but let's just say neutrons and
make it simpler no electric charge
conservation the machine iser for free
so what's that machine is operated for
free so there's no
charge okay so up by itself goes to a
state with two electrons which I'm going
to write as up
up there's two electrons each in the UP
State and I'm just going to write up by
by putting two UPS next to each
other what if I put down in
here what comes out two downs assuming
that I was able to build a Quantum xerox
machine and two downs come
out so down will evolve eventually into
down
down okay now supposing I put an
electron in these this this was an
electron that was pointing up along the
third axis all right so we have our axes
again now I'm going to put in an
electron which happens not to be
oriented along the third axis but what
happens to be oriented along the first
axis the X1 axis all right so what
should I call it instead of down let's
call it left or right right up uh up
down left right and in
out okay so now I want to put in here a
electron pointing to the right in other
words it 90° along the x- axis for
example and if I have a faithful cloning
machine I'm not going to redraw the
cloning machine if I have a faithful
cloning machine it should take right
to right right
right
right okay but what is right what is the
right State the right state is just up
plus
down the divided by < TK of two
right so what I've actually put in on
the left hand side is up plus down over
the square otk of
two up plus down but I know what I get
out out if I put in up if I put in up I
get up up if I put in down I get down
down if the evolution is linear like
this then that already tells me what I
get if I put an up plus down what do I
get
well if I put in up I get up
up if I put in
down let let's write it as
I I get down
down ofun of two so the linearity of
quantum mechanics the fact that the
evolution of states is linear already
tells me what I get if I put an up plus
down I don't have any
choice right but what is right right
let's see if let's see if it agrees what
does right right mean right right means
up plus
down for the first
electron times up plus down for the
second
electron I'm just jux opposing them by
uh the two electrons the first Factor
corresponds to one electron the second
fact that corresponds to the other
electron sorry over square root of
two
okay but when I multiply this out what
do I have here I have a configuration
with two ups up times up I have a
configuration with two downs but I also
have up down and down up
unavoidably if I take two electrons each
with spin along the x axis I will find
if I measure the third component of spin
that some of the times I will find an up
and a Down over here I have two ups and
two downs but never an up and a
down so you see the um the
assumption that you can build a cloning
machine which both clones ups and downs
and also clones lefts and rights is
inconsistent it's inconsistent with the
linearity of quantum
mechanics but what what
if you insist that the the two outputs
have to say it again
the assuming that the two outputs have
to be independent of each other somehow
yeah I'm not sure what it would mean to
clone things unless they were were
cloning things two independent
things well well sorry the the
Assumption was that up produces two ups
and the down produces two
downs yeah but then you you explain the
uh right right to be the product of
the that's the way you build composite
States
that's the way you build States of uh of
independent systems is to multiply the
the state vectors in that fashion it's
called taking we haven't had a time to
do everything unfortunately we haven't
had time to do everything but the
mathematical operation of combining
systems is called tensor product you
take the tensor product of uh of State
vectors and that's what this is this is
the tensor product
of two
rights and then you expand it out and
you see what you get
and what you get cannot be
this so you're right there's a degree of
assuming that the two things are
independent of each other but I'm not
sure what it would mean to clone uh to
clone things if they weren't independent
of each other and then you could do
independent experiments on them so it is
not possible to take a
object uh in a given in an arbitrary
wave function and put it into a machine
and have it come out as a replicas two
replicas of the same thing
a laser is a pretty good cloning device
so where does where does your argument
break down for a
laser uh a laser is a cloning device put
in a put in a photon that has a certain
certain State and you're going to get uh
bunch of them produced it's actually not
true okay sated emission the
polarization of the pair of phons is not
quite the same as the input proton the
vector the linear combination of the
initial magnetic state of the excited
atom plus the incid
stimulating so while the two output
protons are identical they not the same
polarization I have to think about the
question you may be right I have to
think about the question so you say you
take a photon with a given
polarization and you stimulate some
Mission
uh I have to think about what
the analy it from an information VI yeah
information of the excited to
the and that
isise maybe right I have to I'll I'll
think about it this week and see if I
can give you a uh
simple
argument
um however this there there is no
controversy about the fact that you
can't build a cloning machine I think
there is qu contro I don't even know if
it's controversy I think there's a
question of how close you can get how
close can you get to a cloning machine
and I've seen papers saying different
amount different you know some
quantitative measure of how close you
can get and uh there's some number like
three qus that come out you can have a
close P machine that's 3/4 accurate or
some such thing but uh but that's uh
something I don't know much about anyway
this is the basic idea that you can't
have a and the reason is simple
um multiplying two things together like
this taking anything and squaring it is
not a linear operation it's a quadratic
operation you take any state basically
and replicating it is sort of square is
a sort of operation which is
quadratic right it's a operation of not
squaring something but sort of
multiplying it by itself that's that's
what's going on here so what going on
here and that's simply not a linear
operation it can never be linear it's
always quadratic and since all the
evolution of State vectors is always
linear you can't quite all you can't do
it you can build a machine that will
clone ups and downs but then it won't
clone rights and
lefts you can build a ma machine that
will clone rights and lefts it won't
clone ups and
downs you can not duplicate that you may
transfer these properties to yes yes yes
that's a different issue that's a
different issue that you can transport
that you can transfer some information
from one thing to another yes but what
you can't do is duplicate it in two
systems right so you might have some
kind of information for example the
electron is up
and you might want to translate you
might want to transfer that to a photon
and send it and uh the question is how
well can you transfer it to another
system and that that's a separate
question yeah and this whole discussion
I think you have to State somehow that
you don't know the state the when you
try to clone it if you know it if you
know the state and of course you can
clone it so if you know the state you
can build a machine that will clone it
but it will be a different machine then
it for example if I know the state is up
I can build a machine that will clone it
and and the same machine will clone
down if I know the state is right I can
build a machine that will clone it but
the same machine will not clone ups and
rights so yes if you know the state you
can build a thing that uh that clones
it was that the question or answer was
that if you don't know the state then
you cannot clone it you have a certain
practi
it is in a certain State all right but
let me just say yeah yeah but let me
just say it a little a little
differently let me say it a little
differently you cannot build a machine
that will clone anything or that will
clone UPS rights or ins and outs the
same machine cannot clone them all so if
you didn't know what the state was
somebody gave you a state and said no
you don't look at it and you just say I
want to clone
it
uh your machine may just happen to clone
it because it may be the up
thing but uh the chances
are well it wouldn't clone
things I've said it enough times I can't
say it again I'm running out of steam
right the output of the machine would be
what you wrote down last yes but that's
different than what the output of the
machine has to be by quantum
mechanics that's the linear result this
is the cloning result this is the linear
result
result yeah and they're different so one
one they can't be the
same
right in other words just two electrons
both right have in them a piece with an
up down and a down up that's
inconsistent with uh with what the
linearity of quantum mechanics says so
sorry no
clone um it see do I see this it seems
like amount of information containing
two independent entities is different
than an entangled entity and yes this is
true see has like anybody tried to
attach this from that perspective of
information theor I'm sure they
have
um I the last time what I told you is if
you have a single
electron the state vectors are a two
parameter family if you have two
independent electrons which have never
been entangled or anything like that
then the state vectors you would expect
to be a four parameter family but in
fact the state vectors of two electrons
are a six parameter family so there's a
richer class of States now how you do
you want to can you quantify that by
information Theory I don't know I
haven't
uh
uh I'm sure you can well I I certainly
know how to how to quantify the degree
of entanglement of two systems there's
something which I hope we will get to
which is called entanglement
entropy and entanglement entropy is a
measure of the degree of entanglement of
two systems so we can certainly quantify
the amount of entanglement between two
systems I'm not sure if that's what
you're asking but in any case we'll try
to get to that concept of entanglement
entropy okay any other questions before
we go
[Music]
home
the proceeding program is copyrighted by
Stanford University please visit us at
stanford.edu